<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://andreachiocca.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://andreachiocca.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-10-28T13:28:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreachiocca.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Fatigue Assessment through the Effective Critical Plane Factor</title><link href="https://andreachiocca.github.io/2024/09/01/ECP.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fatigue Assessment through the Effective Critical Plane Factor"/><published>2024-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreachiocca.github.io/2024/09/01/ECP</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreachiocca.github.io/2024/09/01/ECP.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Fatigue failures in structural components often result from stress concentrations caused by geometric irregularities such as notches or welds. Various methods like the <strong>Notch Stress Approach (NSA)</strong>, <strong>Theory of Critical Distances (TCD)</strong>, and <strong>Strain Energy Density (SED)</strong> have been used for fatigue strength assessment. However, these methods may not capture the full complexity of the stress-strain field near stress concentrators.</p> <p>We introduce a novel approach, the <strong>Effective Critical Plane (ECP)</strong> method, which enhances fatigue life prediction by averaging the stress-strain field over a small volume around the critical point, preserving the tensorial characteristics of the field. The size of this averaging volume is determined as a material parameter and optimized through experimental data.</p> <h2 id="methodology">Methodology</h2> <p>The ECP method focuses on calculating critical plane parameters starting from an averaged stress or strain tensor over a control volume <d-cite key="Chiocca2024b"></d-cite>. The main steps include:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Finite Element Analysis (FEA)</strong>: Linear elastic simulations identify the critical node, i.e., the node with the maximum CP factor.</li> <li><strong>Stress-Strain Averaging</strong>: The stress and strain tensors are averaged over a spherical volume (3D) or circular area (2D) around the critical node.</li> <li><strong>Control Radius Optimization</strong>: The radius of this control volume, denoted as $r_c$, is determined through a best-fit process against fatigue test data from notched specimens.</li> <li><strong>Critical Plane Factor Calculation</strong>: Using the averaged stress-strain values, the <strong>FS</strong> and <strong>SWT</strong> ECP factors are computed for varying values of rc. The optimal rc is identified by minimizing scatter between predicted and experimental fatigue lives.</li> </ol> <h3 id="key-equations">Key Equations</h3> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Fatemi-Socie (FS) Factor</strong>: \(FS = \frac{\Delta \gamma_{max}}{2} \left(1 + k \frac{\sigma_n}{\sigma_y}\right)\) Where \(\Delta \gamma_{max}\) is the maximum shear strain amplitude, \(\sigma_n\) is the normal stress, and \(k\) is a material constant.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Smith-Watson-Topper (SWT) Factor</strong>: \(SWT = \frac{\Delta \varepsilon_{max}}{2} \sigma_n\) Where \(\Delta \varepsilon_{max}\) is the maximum normal strain amplitude and \(\sigma_n\) is the maximum normal stress.</p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="implementation-in-matlab">Implementation in MATLAB</h3> <p>The method is implemented through a MATLAB script (included as supplementary material). The script performs the following steps:</p> <ol> <li>FEA to determine stress-strain tensors at critical nodes.</li> <li>Averaging these tensors over a control volume.</li> <li>Computing the ECP factors \(\widetilde{FS}\) and \(\widetilde{SWT}\) for each load cycle and control radius.</li> </ol> <h2 id="applications">Applications</h2> <p>The ECP approach has been validated using experimental data from <strong>low carbon steel specimens</strong> subjected to various notches and loading conditions. Two geometries—<strong>U-notched</strong> and <strong>V-notched</strong> specimens—were used in simulations to derive the optimal control radius $r_c$ for the material. The results were compared with traditional methods like NSA, TCD, and SED.</p> <h2 id="results-and-discussion">Results and Discussion</h2> <p>The optimal control radii were found to be:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Fatemi-Socie (FS)</strong>: \(r_c = 0.20 \, mm\)</li> <li><strong>Smith-Watson-Topper (SWT)</strong>: \(r_c = 0.25 \, mm\)</li> </ul> <p>For each geometry, the FS and SWT factors were computed and plotted against the number of cycles to failure. The comparison with experimental data showed that the FS model better describes the fatigue process for ductile materials, as it accounts for shear cracking.</p> <p>A supplementary Matlab® script implementing the method is available on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/achiocca1/ECP">ECP</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrea Chiocca</name></author><category term="fatigue"/><category term="assessment,"/><category term="critical"/><category term="plane,"/><category term="ECP"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An insight into the novel fatigue assessment method using the Effective Critical Plane (ECP) factor.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rapid and Accurate Semi-Analytical Method for Fatigue Assessment</title><link href="https://andreachiocca.github.io/2024/03/05/CP-semy-analytical.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rapid and Accurate Semi-Analytical Method for Fatigue Assessment"/><published>2024-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreachiocca.github.io/2024/03/05/CP-semy-analytical</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreachiocca.github.io/2024/03/05/CP-semy-analytical.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Fatigue assessment remains a crucial concern for designers due to unexpected failures during in-service loading. Critical plane methods identify early crack propagation directions but are computationally demanding when dealing with real-world scenarios, complex geometries, and loading conditions. This study introduces a semi-analytical method to efficiently calculate critical plane factors, particularly for finite element analysis (FEA) under elastic-plastic material behavior and non-proportional loading conditions.</p> <h2 id="critical-plane-factors">Critical Plane Factors</h2> <p>The proposed method <d-cite key="Sgamma2024a"></d-cite> applies to all critical plane factors that require maximization of the entire formulation. In this case two critical plane factors will be used as examples, the extended Fatemi-Socie critical plane factor \(FS\) and the Findley critical plane factor \(FI\):</p> \[FS = \max \left[ \frac{\Delta \gamma}{2} \left( 1 + k_{FS} \frac{\sigma_{n,max}}{\sigma_y} \right) \right]\] \[FI = \Delta \tau + k_{FI} \sigma_{n,max}\] <p>Where:</p> <ul> <li>\(\Delta \gamma\): Shear strain range</li> <li>\(\Delta \tau\): Shear stress range</li> <li>\(\sigma_{n,max}\): Maximum normal stress</li> <li>\(\sigma_y\): Yield strength</li> </ul> <h2 id="standard-plane-scanning-method">Standard Plane Scanning Method</h2> <p>The standard approach involves scanning all possible plane orientations around each node in the finite element model (FEM), which involves rotating the plane in increments and calculating critical plane parameters, resulting in substantial computational demands. Angular increments are typically 10°, but finer grids (5°–8°) are recommended for higher accuracy.</p> <p>The scanning method uses the following rotation matrix:</p> \[R = R_z(\psi) R_y(\theta) = \begin{bmatrix} \cos(\theta) \cos(\psi) &amp; -\sin(\psi) &amp; \cos(\psi) \sin(\theta) \\ \sin(\psi) \cos(\theta) &amp; \cos(\psi) &amp; \sin(\psi) \sin(\theta) \\ -\sin(\theta) &amp; 0 &amp; \cos(\theta) \end{bmatrix}\] <h2 id="semi-analytical-method">Semi-Analytical Method</h2> <p>This novel semi-analytical method discretizes the load-time history as peaks and valleys, defining stress \(\sigma^{(i)}\) and strain \(\varepsilon^{(i)}\) tensors for each loading condition. Successive load conditions \(i\) and \(i+1\) allow the calculation of tensor ranges:</p> \[\Delta \sigma = \sigma^{(i)} - \sigma^{(i+1)}, \: \Delta \varepsilon = \varepsilon^{(i)} - \varepsilon^{(i+1)}\] <p>Principal stress/strain parameters are obtained via eigenvalue analysis, and critical plane orientations are determined by rotating around the principal axes.</p> <p>The rotation matrix for the transformation is:</p> \[R_{\bar{n}_2} = \begin{bmatrix} \cos(\omega) &amp; 0 &amp; \sin(\omega) \\ 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 \\ -\sin(\omega) &amp; 0 &amp; \cos(\omega) \end{bmatrix}\] <p>The method evaluates critical plane parameters along predefined paths in three steps, reducing computational demands compared to the standard scanning method.</p> <h2 id="results-and-discussion">Results and Discussion</h2> <p>Finite element simulations were performed on a notched specimen under proportional and non-proportional loading. The proposed semi-analytical method achieved a 97% reduction in computation time compared to the standard plane scanning method, while maintaining high accuracy (error &lt; 0.5%). The method was validated by comparing it with the standard plane scanning results under different loading conditions.</p> <p>The performance index \(PI\), defined as:</p> \[PI = \left( 1 - \frac{t_{sa}}{t_{ps}} \right)\] <p>where \(t_{sa}\) is the computation time for the semi-analytical method and \(t_{ps}\) is for the plane scanning method, shows the efficiency of the proposed approach.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>This semi-analytical method for critical plane evaluation significantly reduces computational time while retaining accuracy, making it a promising tool for complex FEM fatigue assessments under multiaxial, non-proportional, and elastic-plastic loading conditions. The method’s simplicity allows for easy implementation in existing computational tools.</p> <p>A supplementary Matlab® script implementing the method is available on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/achiocca1/SeAn-CP">SeAn-CP</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrea Chiocca</name></author><category term="fatigue"/><category term="assessment,"/><category term="critical"/><category term="plane,"/><category term="semi-analytical"/><category term="method"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A semi-analytical method for fatigue assessment using critical plane methods under non-proportional loading and material plasticity.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Closed-Form Solution for the Evaluation of CP Factor and CP Orientation</title><link href="https://andreachiocca.github.io/2023/03/18/CP-evaluation-closed-form.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Closed-Form Solution for the Evaluation of CP Factor and CP Orientation"/><published>2023-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreachiocca.github.io/2023/03/18/CP-evaluation-closed-form</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreachiocca.github.io/2023/03/18/CP-evaluation-closed-form.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>In this post, we present an optimized method for evaluating the Critical Plane (CP) factor and determining CP orientation for fatigue analysis under multiaxial loading conditions. This approach is based on an efficient algorithm that streamlines the identification of the maximum shear strain amplitude and normal stress, aligning with critical plane criteria such as the Fatemi-Socie CP factor. The method is ideal for structural components with complex geometries, such as notched specimens, and significantly reduces calculation time while maintaining accuracy.</p> <p>The application of this method can be found detailed in some of the author’s publications: Chiocca et al. <d-cite key="Chiocca2023"></d-cite>, <d-cite key="Chiocca2023a"></d-cite>,<d-cite key="Chiocca2024c"></d-cite>, <d-cite key="Chiocca2024"></d-cite>.</p> <h2 id="theoretical-background">Theoretical Background</h2> <p>The Fatemi-Socie CP factor (\(FS\)) <d-cite key="Fatemi1988"></d-cite> is considered as a reference:</p> \[FS=\frac{\Delta \gamma}{2} \left( 1 + k \frac{\sigma_{n,max}}{S_y} \right)\] <p>where \(k\) is the material parameter found by fitting the uniaxial experimental data against the pure torsion data, \(\Delta \gamma\) is the shear strain range, \(\sigma_{n,max}\) is the normal stress acting on the plane where the shear strain range is evaluated and \(S_y\) is the material yield strength.</p> <p>In fatigue analysis, the stress and strain tensors for the \(i-th\) loading condition are defined as follows:</p> \[\mathbf{\sigma}^i = \begin{bmatrix} \sigma_{xx}^i &amp; \tau_{xy}^i &amp; \tau_{xz}^i \\ \tau_{yx}^i &amp; \sigma_{yy}^i &amp; \tau_{yz}^i \\ \tau_{zx}^i &amp; \tau_{zy}^i &amp; \sigma_{zz}^i \\ \end{bmatrix}, \; \mathbf{\varepsilon}^i = \begin{bmatrix} \varepsilon_{xx}^i &amp; \frac{\gamma_{xy}^i}{2} &amp; \frac{\gamma_{xz}^i}{2} \\ \frac{\gamma_{yx}^i}{2} &amp; \varepsilon_{yy}^i &amp; \frac{\gamma_{yz}^i}{2} \\ \frac{\gamma_{zx}^i}{2} &amp; \frac{\gamma_{zy}^i}{2} &amp; \varepsilon_{zz}^i \\ \end{bmatrix}\] <p>The strain tensor range, considering two successive loading conditions \(i\) and \(i+1\), is computed as the difference between the two strain tensors:</p> \[\mathbf{\Delta \varepsilon} = \mathbf{\varepsilon}^i - \mathbf{\varepsilon}^{i+1}\] <h2 id="equations-and-method">Equations and Method</h2> <h3 id="principal-strain-calculation">Principal Strain Calculation</h3> <p>To evaluate the principal strain tensor range (\(\Delta\varepsilon_{1}\), \(\Delta\varepsilon_{2}\), \(\Delta\varepsilon_{3}\)), we compute the eigenvalues of the matrix \(\mathbf{\Delta \varepsilon}\):</p> \[\mathbf{\Delta\varepsilon} = \begin{bmatrix} \Delta\varepsilon_{xx} &amp; \frac{\Delta\gamma_{xy}}{2} &amp; \frac{\Delta\gamma_{xz}}{2} \\ \frac{\Delta\gamma_{yx}}{2} &amp; \Delta\varepsilon_{yy} &amp; \frac{\Delta\gamma_{yz}}{2} \\ \frac{\Delta\gamma_{zx}}{2} &amp; \frac{\Delta\gamma_{zy}}{2} &amp; \Delta\varepsilon_{zz} \\ \end{bmatrix} = \begin{bmatrix} \Delta\varepsilon_{1} &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; \Delta\varepsilon_{2} &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; \Delta\varepsilon_{3} \\ \end{bmatrix}\] <p>The principal strains \(\Delta\varepsilon_{1}\), \(\Delta\varepsilon_{2}\), and \(\Delta\varepsilon_{3}\) represent the maximum, intermediate, and minimum normal strains, respectively, in their corresponding principal directions. These directions are defined by the eigenvectors of the strain tensor \(\mathbf{\Delta\varepsilon}\).</p> <h3 id="eigenvectors">Eigenvectors</h3> <p>The eigenvectors corresponding to the principal strains define the orientation of the planes on which these principal strains act. These eigenvectors are represented as the columns of the eigenvector matrix \(R_p\):</p> \[R_p = \begin{bmatrix} n_{11} &amp; n_{12} &amp; n_{13}\\ n_{21} &amp; n_{22} &amp; n_{23}\\ n_{31} &amp; n_{32} &amp; n_{33}\\ \end{bmatrix}\] <ul> <li>The first column vector, \(\mathbf{n}_1 = \begin{bmatrix} n_{11} \\ n_{21} \\ n_{31} \end{bmatrix}\), corresponds to the principal direction associated with the maximum principal strain \(\Delta\varepsilon_{1}\).</li> <li>The second column vector, \(\mathbf{n}_2 = \begin{bmatrix} n_{12} \\ n_{22} \\ n_{32} \end{bmatrix}\), corresponds to the direction of the intermediate principal strain \(\Delta\varepsilon_{2}\).</li> <li>The third column vector, \(\mathbf{n}_3 = \begin{bmatrix} n_{13} \\ n_{23} \\ n_{33} \end{bmatrix}\), corresponds to the direction of the minimum principal strain \(\Delta\varepsilon_{3}\).</li> </ul> <p>These eigenvectors define the orientation of the principal planes (the planes on which no shear strain occurs) and are used to establish the local coordinate system for evaluating the Critical Plane.</p> <h3 id="maximum-shear-strain">Maximum Shear Strain</h3> <p>The maximum shear strain range \(\Delta\gamma_{max}\) is calculated as:</p> \[\frac{\Delta\gamma_{max}}{2} = \frac{(\Delta\varepsilon_{1} - \Delta\varepsilon_{3})}{4}\] <h3 id="rotation-for-critical-plane-orientation">Rotation for Critical Plane Orientation</h3> <p>To adjust the reference system for proper plane alignment, a rotation by \(\omega = \frac{\pi}{4}\) about the local \(y\)-axis is applied, resulting in the following rotation matrix:</p> \[R_y = \begin{bmatrix} \cos(\frac{\pi}{4}) &amp; 0 &amp; \sin(\frac{\pi}{4})\\ 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0\\ -\sin(\frac{\pi}{4}) &amp; 0 &amp; \cos(\frac{\pi}{4})\\ \end{bmatrix}\] <p>The final rotation matrix, $R$, defining the CP orientation is obtained by multiplying \(R_p\) with \(R_y\):</p> \[R = R_pR_y\] <h3 id="maximum-normal-stress-sigma_ntextmax">Maximum Normal Stress ($\sigma_{n,\text{max}}$)</h3> <p>The maximum normal stress, \(\sigma_{n,\text{max}}\), on the critical plane is calculated by projecting the stress tensor \(\mathbf{\sigma}\) onto the normal vector \(\mathbf{n}\) of the critical plane. The normal vectors to the critical plane are two in this case represented by \(\mathbf{\widetilde{n_1}}=R(:,1)\) or \(\mathbf{\widetilde{n_3}}=R(:,3)\). The normal stress is computed as follows:</p> \[\sigma_{n,\text{max}} = \max \left( \mathbf{\widetilde{n_1}}^T \mathbf{\sigma} \mathbf{\widetilde{n_1}},\mathbf{\widetilde{n_3}}^T \mathbf{\sigma} \mathbf{\widetilde{n_3}} \right)\] <h2 id="application-example">Application Example</h2> <p>This method has been applied to various notched specimens subjected to multiaxial loading, and under elastic-plastic material hypotesis. The approach not only accurately predicts fatigue life but also demonstrates a significant reduction in computational effort compared to traditional critical plane evaluation methodologies.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>This optimized algorithm for evaluating CP factors and determining the orientation of critical planes enhances the efficiency of fatigue assessments, especially for components under complex multiaxial loading conditions. The approach has been successfully validated against experimental data and offers practical advantages in engineering applications.</p> <p>A supplementary Matlab® script implementing the method is available on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/achiocca1/CPOpt-v1.0">CPOpt</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Andrea Chiocca</name></author><category term="fatigue"/><category term="evaluation,"/><category term="critical"/><category term="plane,"/><category term="strain"/><category term="tensor"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A detailed explanation of an efficient method for evaluating the Critical Plane (CP) factor and orientation.]]></summary></entry></feed>